Guide to the Walter Strickland Thornber Papers and Photographs 1900-1915
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Walter Strickland Thornber Papers and Photographs
1900-1915
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
PC 202
Thornber, Walter Strickland, 1874-1959
7 Linear feet of shelf space 13 Boxes
This collection includes documents, glass plate negatives, photographs, and lantern slides of fruit, orchards, and other agricultural subjects dating from 1900 to 1915. These were created by Walter Thornber during his time as professor of horticulture with Washington State University and their Agricultural Experiment Station, and as a horticulturalist in the Lewiston-Clarkston valley.
Walter Strickland Thornber (1874-1959) was born in Illinois and received both his Bachelor and Master of Science degrees from South Dakota Agricultural College (today’s South Dakota State University) by 1899 and served on the faculty there until 1904. Special studies at Cornell University followed and resulted in a Master of Science degree in Agriculture. In 1900 Thornber married Phoebe Hough, who died two years later. With his second wife Ethelyn Henry, Thornber had two sons, Gordon and Merrill, and two daughters Evelyn and Georgeann. In spring 1905, Thornber accepted an appointment as Professor of Horticulture at Washington State College and horticulturist for the Washington Agricultural Experiment Station (WAES) at the college.
As horticulturist with WAES, Thornber continued the farmers’ institutes and demonstration trains begun by predecessors and wrote WAES bulletins such as 1910’s “Cherries in Washington.” Glass-plate negatives in this collection furnished some of the prints in Thornber’s bulletins. Thornber also conducted research on fruit varieties suitable for local conditions in an already established experimental orchard.
Thornber served as horticulture faculty and department head at WSC and horticulturalist with WAES until the summer of 1911 when he resigned to become a consulting horticulturist in the Lewiston-Clarkston Valley. There, in the first two decades of the century, the Lewiston-Clarkston Improvement Company (LCIC) and the Lewiston Land and Water Company (LLWC), secured water and land rights in order to irrigate and then sell orchard plots to those who “come here for a common purpose, that of making homes in an orchard community for congenial conditions.”
These companies had solicited Thornber’s advice before he moved from Pullman to the valley, but by 1911 they convinced him to move south where he could work more directly with each company to plan the orchard plots and offer short courses about fruit choices and care under the auspices of the Lewiston-Clarkston School of Horticulture, of which Thornber was made the director. Thornber lectured daily on orchard management, combatting pests, and other topics of interest to budding valley orchardists. LLWC planned to devote about six thousand of its thirty thousand or so acres in the Lewiston-Clarkston Valley to experimental orchards and vineyards which would also be used for laboratory instruction on pruning, spraying, grafting, and so on.
National and state support for agricultural extension work coincided with the diminishment of Thornber’s consulting work and brought him back to Pullman in 1915. The State of Washington had provided funding for agricultural extension work at the experiment station in Pullman and by 1911 the college’s Board of Regents separated the agricultural extension work from the experiment station. With that division, came the need to hire specialists within the Agricultural Extension Service. In 1914 the federal government responded to the demand for more extension work with the Smith-Lever Act that granted money to each land-grant school for agricultural extension work. This attention to the importance of extension work drew Thornber back to Pullman and Washington State College in 1915 as the Director of Agricultural Extension.
Thornber worked at WSC from 1905 until 1911 when he left to work as the Horticulturist for the Leswiston-Clarkston School of Horticulture. He returned to Pullman in 1915 as the director of the Washington Agricultural and Home Economics Extension Service. He again left in 1919 to return to Lewiston to become a full-time fruit grower. Walter S. Thornber died of a stroke April 1, 1959 in his home in Lewiston, Idaho.
This collection includes documents, glass plate negatives, photographs, and lantern slides of fruit, orchards, and other agricultural subjects dating from 1900 to 1915, with the bulk dating from the 1905 to 1911 period when Thornber was in the Horticulture Department at Washington State College and horticulturist for the college’s Washington Agricultural Experiment Station, and dealing with his work there.
Contained in this collection are four boxes of paper documents related to specific fruits and agricultural notes on fruit production, 746 glass plate negatives (with a few film negatives) and 41 photo prints of images relating to fruit production and other various agricultural products, and 109 instructional lantern slides of cement products and images of houses.
Series one consists of paper documents, in two subseries. Subseries one is personal papers and notes, including crop records, lecture notes, agricultural topic specific notes, and fruit specific. Subseries two consists of fruit-specific observations, separated into four subcategories: fruit lists of varieties, primarily apples, grapes, and plums; cross-sections of fruits, primarily apples; written descriptions of fruit trees, again primarily apples; and crop records.
Series two is the bulk of the collection, and consists of photographs, primarily glass plate negatives. These are arranged into subseries by format. Subseries one consists of glass plate negatives and photographs and primarily consists of images of fruit, fruit trees, and other agricultural subjects. Each plate was given a subject identifier and grouped together based on the subjects, such as apples, blackberries, landscapes, people, trees (non-fruit), etc. Subseries two contains lantern slides, primarily instructional, split into three subcategories: concrete promotional slides, hand-drawn agricultural cartoons, and interiors and exteriors of various homes.
In box nine, included with the glass plates of People, there are a select few Thornber family photographs, including glass negatives of Thornber and Hough around the time of their marriage and of Gordon and Merrill as boys.
The collection is arranged in two series. Series one consists of paper documents, in two subseries, both arranged alphabetically by subject. Series two consists of photographs, primarily glass plate negatives, arranged into subseries by format. Glass plates are arranged alphabetically by subject, and usually include the original labeled envelope they came in. Included in this sub-series are photograph prints, which retain original order and are housed directly after the glass plates. The concrete promotional slides and the cartoon slides retain original order. The lantern slides of shots of the homes have numbered labels on them and are arranged numerically based off of those labels.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Gordon Thornber, son of Walter Strickland Thornber, donated the papers and photographs to Washington State University Libraries in 1986 (MS.1986.38).
Agricultural Research Center Office Files 1901-1948 (Archives 20)
Lewiston-Clarkston Improvement Company Records 1888-1963 (Cage 311)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Thornber, Walter Strickland, 1874-1959 -- Archives
Fruit trees -- Washington (State); Fruit culture -- Washington (State); Orchards -- Washington (State); Agricultural experiment stations -- Washington (State)
Agriculture; Washington (State); Photographs
- Series 1. Paper Documents
  - Subseries 1.1: Personal Papers and Notes
    - Apple. Notes on apple production and fruit growth. A typed list of apple varieties that accompanies these notes., Undated (Box 1, Tape 1)
    - Cherry. General notes on cherry growth and production., Undated (Box 1, Tape 2)
    - Cover crops. Hand-written notes on cover crops and their benefits for agricultural production., Undated (Box 1, Tape 3)
    - Cover crop s. Typed notes on cover crops and their benefits for agricultural production., Undated (Box 1, Tape 3)
    - Cultivation. Handwritten notes containing notes on "Philosophy of Tillage," "Orchard Tillage," "Saving and Adding Fertility," "Soil Moisture.” Also includes program for 5th Annual Short Course in Agriculture and Horticulture in North Yakima, December 1916., Undated, 1916 (Box 1, Tape 4)
    - Dwarf Fruit. Handwritten notes., Undated (Box 1, Tape 5)
    - Fertilizers. Notes on fertilizer types and application., Undated (Box 1, Tape 6)
    - Horticultural library. List of horticultural resources., Undated (Box 1, Tape 7)
    - Intercropping young orchards. Notes on plants to intercrop in orchards., Undated (Box 1, Tape 8)
    - Intercropping young orchards. Notes on plants to intercrop in the Lewiston and Clarkston area., Undated (Box 1, Tape 8)
    - Lecture notes and outline. For Lewiston Orchards Producer’s Association on the topic of Building an Agricultural Community., Undated (Box 1, Tape 9)
    - Lewiston-Clarkston School of Horticulture. Outlines the state of the orchards in Lewiston-Clarkston and how Thornber will be working with the Lewiston-Clarkston School of Horticulture., 1911 (Box 1, Tape 10)
    - Marketing of fruit., Undated (Box 1, Tape 11)
    - Miscellaneous. Notes on “Industrial Education at the College.”, Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Notes on “Orchard Diversification.”, Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Personal correspondence., Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. “What ‘System on the Farm’ will do for men who own their farms or for farm managers.”, Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Apple notes., Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Hand-written notes on “The Beautifying of Home Grounds.”, Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Notes on “Pruning for Fruit Every Year.”, Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Raspberry price list., Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Program for “Short Course in Fruit Growing.”, 1910 (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Two programs and notes for “Fifth Annual Short Course in Agriculture and Horticulture.”, Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Newsletter of “Extension News Service: The State College of Washington”, Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Fruit lists with multiple fruits., Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Miscellaneous. Postcards for the Thornber Orchards, Undated (Box 1, Tape 12)
    - Orchard Protection. Notes and pamphlets on how to deal with various threats, 1912, undated (Box 1, Tape 13)
    - Orchard Management. Loose notes., Undated (Box 1, Tape 13)
    - Peach. Notes on production and growth., 1910, undated (Box 1, Tape 14)
    - Pests. Notes about the “Codling Moth.”, Undated (Box 1, Tape 15)
    - Pests. Common orchard pests, what plants they affect, and how to treat them., 1908-1911, 1912, 1915, undated (Box 1, Tape 15)
    - Pests. Including State College of Washington Spraying calendar for Spring 1912., 1908-1912, 1915, undated (Box 1, Tape 15)
    - Planting Plans. One diagram including plot dimensions for planting and 22 grid diagrams of various plans for orchard layouts., Undated (Box 1, Tape 16)
    - Plum. Nine photos of plums and plum trees; notes on growth and production., 1900, 1911, undated (Box 1, Tape 17)
    - Raspberry and Blackberry. General notes on the growth and production., 1908, undated (Box 1, Tape 18)
    - Walnut. Brochures/catalogs on walnuts and walnut orchards., 1912-1913, undated (Box 1, Tape 19)
    - Walnut. Correspondence on English Walnut Tree with E.C. Pomeroy and with Daniel N. Pomeroy., 1912-1913, undated (Box 1, Tape 19)
    - Walnut. General notes on walnut growth and production., Undated (Box 1, Tape 19)
  - Subseries 1.2: Fruit Specific Observations.
    - Subseries 1.2.1: Fruit Variety Lists.
      - Apple fruit list. Handwritten lists of apple varieties., Undated (Box 2, Tape 1)
      - Grapes. Handwritten list of grape varieties; general notes on grape growth and production., 1904 (Box 2, Tape 2)
      - Plum fruit list. Typed and alphabetized list of varieties., Undated (Box 2, Tape 3)
    - Subseries 1.2.2: Fruit Cross-Sections
      - Apple cross-sections by variety. BCD., circa 1904 -1913 (Box 2, Tape 4)
      - Apple cross-sections by variety. EFG., circa 1904 -1913 (Box 2, Tape 5)
      - Apple cross-sections by variety. HIJK., circa 1904 -1913 (Box 2, Tape 6)
      - Apple cross-sections by variety. LM., circa 1904 -1913 (Box 2, Tape 7)
      - Apple cross-sections by variety. NOPRSTUW., circa 1904 -1913 (Box 2, Tape 8)
      - Apple cross-sections, created by WSC Students. Various apple types., 1909-1910 (Box 2, Tape 9)
      - Apple cross Sections. Conical. Cross-sections of apples, axial and transverse. All with "conical" form., Undated and ca.1909-1910 (Box 2, Tape 10)
      - Apple cross-sections. Northwestern Greening Group, an apple variety., 1910,Undated (Box 2, Tape 11)
      - Apple cross-sections. Oblate. Cross-sections of apples, axial and transverse. All with "oblate" form., circa 1909 (Box 2, Tape 12)
      - Apple cross-sections. Oblong. Cross-sections pf apples, axial and transverse. All with "oblong" form., Undated, ca.1909-1910 (Box 2, Tape 13)
      - Apple cross-sections. Round. Cross-sections of apples, axial and transverse. All with "round" form., Undated, circa 1909-1910 (Box 2, Tape 14)
      - Apple cross-sections. Unclassified. Cross-sections of apples, axial and transverse. Unclassified by shape., circa 1909 (Box 2, Tape 15)
      - Apple cross-sections. Unclassified and numbered. Cross-sections of apples, axial and transverse. Unclassified by shape. With page numbers., circa 1909 (Box 2, Tape 16)
      - Crabapple Cross-sections. Includes notes., circa 1905-1910 (Box 2, Tape 17)
      - Crabapple Cross-Sections. Includes “Description of Russian Crab Trees on Department Grounds.”, Undated (Box 2, Tape 17)
      - Crabapple Cross-sections. Two cards that track the year, crop, ripe, condition, and notes for crabapple trees., 1905 -1910 (Box 2, Tape 17)
      - “Summer Apples Harvested” list, and unlabeled apple cross-sections. Cross-sections of various apple varieties, including an unlabeled group, Blue Pearmain, and Jonathan Group., 1909-1910 (Box 2, Tape 18)
      - “Summer Apples Harvested” list, and unlabeled apple cross-sections. "Summer Apples harvested before 20th of August.”, Undated (Box 2, Tape 18)
      - Pear cross-section., 1913 (Box 2, Tape 19)
    - Subseries 1.2.3: Fruit Tree Descriptions
      - Apples. “A”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 1)
      - Apples. “B”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 2)
      - Apples. “C”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 3)
      - Apples. “D”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 4)
      - Apples. “E”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 5)
      - Apples. “F”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 6)
      - Apples. “G”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 7)
      - Apples. “H”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 8)
      - Apples. “IJ”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 9)
      - Apples. “K”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 10)
      - Apples. “L”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 11)
      - Apples. “MN”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 12)
      - Apples. “O”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 13)
      - Apples. “PQR”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 14)
      - Apples. “ST”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 15)
      - Apples. “UVW”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 16)
      - Apples. “YZ”. Organized by variety; includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 17)
      - Peach. Includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 18)
      - Plum. Drawing and description of a plum, including source, size, color, skin, juice, flavor, etc., 1907 (Box 3, Tape 19)
      - Plum and Prunes. Includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 20)
      - Prunus. Includes descriptions for age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 21)
      - Unspecific fruit tree descriptions. Includes age, form, size, branches, buds, etc., Undated (Box 3, Tape 22)
    - Subseries 1.2.4: Crop Records.
      - Crop Records. These include the fruit variety, condition of the crop, when the crop was ripe, condition of the tree, and notes., 1909-1910 (Box 4)
- Series 2. Images
  - Subseries 2.1: Glass Plate Negatives and Photo Prints
    - Subseries 2.1.1: Glass Plate Negatives
      - Alfalfa., Undated; 2 items (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
      - Almond., Undated; 1 items (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Apple. Includes trees and fruit., Ca. 1906. 1912, undated; 52 items (Box 5, Folder 4-55)
      - Apricot. Includes trees and fruit., Ca. 1907, undated; 8 items (Box 5, Folder 56-63)
      - Blackberry. Includes plants and fruit., 1908-1909, undated; 15 items (Box 5, Folder 64-78)
      - Buildings., 1909, undated; 12 items (Box 5, Folder 79-90)
      - Cantaloupe, Rocky Ford., Undated; 1 items (Box 5, Folder 91)
      - Carrots., 1906, undated; 3 items (Box 5, Folder 92-94)
      - Cherry. Includes trees and fruit., 1907, 1911, undated; 17 items (Box 5, Folder 95-111)
      - Cherry. Includes trees and fruit., 1907, 1909, undated; 72 items (Box 6, Folder 1-72)
      - Chestnuts. Film negatives., Undated; 1 items (Box 6, Folder 73)
      - Cranberry. Includes trees and fruit., Undated; 7 items (Box 6, Folder 74-80)
      - Currant. Includes trees and fruit., 1909; 7 items (Box 6, Folder 81-87)
      - Disease, non-plant specific. Shot hole fungi on twigs from unspecified fruit trees., 1909; 2 items (Box 6, Folder 88-89)
      - Equipment. Includes fruit refrigerator, pony-drawn refrigerator., Undated; 3 items (Box 6, Folder 90-92)
      - Flowers., 1906, undated; 17 items (Box 6, Folder 93-109)
      - Gooseberry., 1908 - 1909; 7 items (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
      - Grape., 1907, 1908, 1909, 1911, undated; 88 items (Box 7, Folder 8-95)
      - Kohlrabi., 1906; 1 items (Box 7, Folder 96)
      - Labor, agricultural., 1907, undated; 7 items (Box 7, Folder 97-103)
      - Landscapes, Washington and Idaho., 1907, 1909, undated; 12 items (Box 7, Folder 104-115)
      - Loganberry., 1907; 3 items (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
      - Mushroom., Undated; 2 items (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
      - Nectarine., 1908, undated; 3 items (Box 8, Folder 6 -8)
      - Peach., ca. 1906. 1912, undated; 102 items (Box 8, Folder 9-110)
      - Pear., ca. 1097. 1912, undated; 85 items (Box 9, Folder 1-85)
      - People. Includes Thornber’s students, family, and local citizens., ca. 1909. 1913, undated; 27 items (Box 9, Folder 86 -112)
      - Pest damage. Includes wooly aphids, gophers, and moles., Undated; 3 items (Box 9, Folder 113-115)
      - Phenomenal Berrr., Undated; 1 items (Box 9, Folder 116)
      - Plum., ca. 1906. 1912, undated; 38 items (Box 10, Folder 1-38)
      - Potato., 1906; 12 items (Box 10, Folder 39-50)
      - Prune., 1906, 1908, 1909, 1910, undated; 27 items (Box 10, Folder 51-77)
      - Raspberry., 1907, undated; 10 items (Box 10, Folder 78. 87)
      - Squash. Cross-sections and staged images., 1096, undated; 2 items (Box 10, Folder 88- 89)
      - Strawberry., 1908; 2 items (Box 10, Folder 90-91)
      - Trees, non-fruit., 1907, 1908, 1909, undated; 27 items (Box 10, Folder 92 -118)
      - Trees, non-fruit., 1907, 1908, undated; 16 items (Box 11, Folder 1-16)
      - Walnut. Includes nuts and trees., 1906, 1907, 1909, undated; 30 items (Box 11, Folder 17-46)
      - Loganberries, raspberries, and wild blackberries., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 47)
      - Peaches and apples, Wenatchee., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 48)
      - Peach and cherry neglect, Clarkston., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 49)
      - Peaches and grapes, Kennewick., 1909; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 50)
      - A peach and a pear from bud., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 51)
      - “Stuarts Field Monroe.”, Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 52)
      - “Howells Grown by Robt. Chabat Moclips.”, Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 53)
      - “Wind following the work of a single tree.”, Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 54)
      - “Tree Trunk.”, Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 55)
      - “Tree crotched Nov. 1909.”, 1 items (Box 11, Folder 56)
      - “Butler’s Farm.”, Undated; 2 items (Box 11, Folder 57-58)
    - Subseries 2.1.2: Empty envelopes and an unidentified negative. These have been retained on the chance they prove useful in identifying unlabeled images.
      - “Grapes, Wenatchee.”, Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 59)
      - “Grape, Name Unknown at LaFollettes.”, Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 60)
      - “Grape vine, LaFollettes July 07.”, 1907; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 61)
      - “Indian Runners.”, Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 62)
      - “Shot Hole Fungi on peach twig.”, Undated; 2 items (Box 11, Folder 63-64)
      - “Potato selection 60.”, 1906; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 65)
      - “Radishes WSC May ‘06.”, 1906; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 66)
    - Subseries 2.1.3: Photographic Prints
      - Unidentified film negatives including images of orchards and of the Thornber family, including 3 prints of people in a field., Undated; 11 items (Box 11, Folder 67)
      - Train with crowd of men and women standing beside it on the tracks., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 68)
      - Crowd of men and women standing beside a train with banners that read "Demonstration Train of Washington.", Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 69)
      - An unidentified tree., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 70)
      - Cherries., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 71)
      - A bridge., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 72)
      - A group of men stand outside near a grouping of trees., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 73)
      - A cluster of trees in a field., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 74)
      - A house., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 75)
      - A large tree surrounded by smaller trees., Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 76)
      - A group of men and women gathering around a train with banners that read "Demonstration Train of Washington.", Undated; 1 items (Box 11, Folder 77)